Great, so now I want to introduce a notion
of something called the optimal value function
so any questions about the bellman equations.
All crystal clear right so if I give you an
MDP and ask you to form the valve in equation
solve it and give me the value function Vpi
can you do that?
I will give you a pi also can you solve it
and give me a V pi, maybe?
kind of computers, oh and we're at some point
I'm going to give you like MDP's with millions
of states and ask you to compute a value function
server, don't try to do that on paper.
So maybe we should give them the head management
program, you think we should?
Did he do the head management when he did
the course?
I don't think so right so this is that's a
problem that we formulated when I was once
a TA or Andy right, so he wanted people to
appreciate how hard it is for how hard is
to solve dynamic programming how hard is to
solve MDP's, large MDP and this was a problem
that was inspired by a real-life problem some
sheep or farmers like dairy farmers in New
Zealand actually solved, okay.
So they had lots of cows and they have to
decide when to milk cows and you know, when
meant to use a cause for something else I
got an Indian now becoming a political statement,
right but yeah so I think sheep, okay.
So when you milk the cow and when do you retire
the cows you know so, they have to figure
out so let us assume that cows have a retirement
home and, so that's the process that's a problem
so then the cows could be young you know they
could be in breedable they could be old when
they were like something like 14 or 17 different
states that they had the cows be in right,
and then they have rewards, okay if you can
milk the cow in a particular state then you
get so much milk, you know if you milk a cow
in a later stage the milk comes down blah
blah blah right, so the whole bunch of things
and there's a small probability that old what
have been classified as old cows also have
a calf, you know me so basically they become
milk able and so all kinds a very complex
situation.
And somebody actually wrote the paper out
of this, they wrote a research paper out of
solving this problem, how do you cast it as
a as an MDP and then come up with a way of
solving it because when in that case when
you actually cast it as an MDP ended up with
like a few million variables, few million
states not variables a few million states
and how do you go about solving the problem
it was not all clear.
So what we did was we came up with a very
simplified version of it, there were instead
of like 17 states there are 3 states in which
the cows could be right and the transition
dynamics were much much simplified right.
So it could from young it could become breed
able and it could pick up old and then from
old it could become breed able again so it
doesn't become n and so, so they're like a
very few transition and so on so forth but
it still turns out that you have to for computing
the exact transition probabilities right you
have to come up with a combinatorial summation
right, it's actually it turns out to be incredibly
hard to get the right transition probabilities
just the P alone and everything else is simple,
we give you what the state is we give you
what the action is right, just coming up with
the P and the R the exact closed expression
for P and
R itself turns out to be a very very hard
problem, right.
And it's not, it's not so there are I don't
know about 300 states or something or 158
states, it is a small problem right but computing
that transition probability even when it is
just 158 states computing the transition probability
turns out to require a combinatorial some
rights little tricky.
So many people actually fail in getting the
right transition probability they would write
the correct code for solving the problem right
but then they would not know how to compute
the transition probability, just to get you'd
appreciate the difficulty of coming up with
that p and therefore, you will appreciate
why reinforcement learning algorithms are
useful because they can work without the p.
So what is optimal here what am I talking
about as being optimal so, whenever talked
about that so far right so what is optimality
in the context of MDP's or in the context
of RL so, we already talked about optimality
in the context of RL what is optimality in
the context of RL?
I want the ? such that for no other pi can
I get a better return than expected return
than this pi right, so I want a ? right so,
I want a pi that is the best overall pi what
should be the quantity here?
But that is not defined.
We know that right, so the expectation over
return does not make sense, so what should
I do?
Should I qualify it over a state right, I
should talk about where I start the return
and then I can take expectations over that
or whatever.
But even better I can do this point wise so
what do I mean by that you can say I need
something like this, pi ,thanks yeah this
is on the flight translation problems edition
one has R t capital R t is written okay, and
finishing to capital G t is written anyway
so this is this is what I am looking for right
and we know what that quantity inside there
is right, so point wise i am trying to find
max over pi, Vpi (s) for all is right, so
this is I want a state I mean I want a policy
that achieves the maximum value for every
state right.
So i am going to call this yeah i am going
to call this pi star right.
If I yeah I can do organized so one thing
one caveat to note here is that arc max might
not return a unique ?, that could be multiple
policies for which this maximum is achieved
in which case any one of them can be called
the optimal policy.
So there is no optimal policy right but that
is an optimal policy that could be multiple
optimal policies, just remember that it went
very simple.
I can give you, think of like a grid well,
so this is something we will revisit often
right.
let us say that every state has four actions
I can go up down left or right wait then every
action is going to get a reward of- one right,
and in the data ballistic world so if I go
up I will move up by one square and if you
go right I will go right by one square and
so on so forth, like in the indicator directions
or you could think of a stochastic world where
you're trying to go up with probability point
9 I will go up the probability point 1, i'll
just stay where i am and you can think of
this as some wheels slipping when you have
a bought that is trying to move forward and
with some probability that we wheel slip and
then you stay in the same place and you probably
have to try moving again and again until you
succeed right.
So you could think of it that way right that
is a stochastic world and every time you make
an action regardless of whether you move or
not, you get a -1 right, so if we try to go
up in the top row, what will happen?
You stay there whether the action succeeds
or not will stay there and you will get a
lot of -1 okay.
So and this is an episodic task right, the
whole thing will end when you reach the state
mark G right so what will be behaving optimally
here we get to G as quickly as possible right,
so the shortest path to G alright so, that
is be the optimal way of behaving in this
world right.
So how many optimal ways are there of behaving
in this world?
A policy is a mapping from States to actions
it doesn't matter very structural but this
is the mark of earnest right so we are assuming
everything is Marco is really shouldn't depend
on very start from right so, so regardless
of where I start from for example when I am
here the optimal action is to go this way
wait I do not care whether they started here
and came here or whether i am starting here
or not right regardless of where I'm starting
the action is like that likewise, okay things
become interesting from here okay.
The number of optimal policies we have so,
any one of these states i can choose any one
of those actions right so, basically i have
about 12 states and I can choose choose any
of the two actions in those 12 states right
so, I have a huge number of optimal policies
right you can convince yourself these are
optimal because they will take me to the expected
number of steps if it is deterministic well,
I can tell you exactly how many steps it will
take me but if it is a stochastic world depending
on what is the probability of failure of the
action right I'll have some probability of
reaching the goal right, so great.
So there are too many optimal policies it
says something common across these entire
policies okay and can you rephrase it?
okay not in terms of steps terms of something
else that we know net reward the expected
reward is going to be the same so for any
state regardless of what is the optimal policy
I choose to execute the value of the state
will be the same, correct is it clear?
Regardless of the policy I choose to execute
the value of the state is going to be the
same correct so i can write this
and I got rid of the ? star here, I am going
to call this V star and V star is unique given
an MDP V star will be unique right.
pi star need not be unique, but regardless
of how many different pi star you have right
V star is going to be the same whichever pi
star you consider V star will be the same
so regardless of V pi star regardless of the
pi star you choose I am going to call the
optimal value function as V star okay, so
this is called the so this is an optimal policy
its optimal value function is I said clear
,there's only one thing which you guys should
be asking me now how do I know that the same
pi will reach the max across all s, so if
you have finite MDP's, it is actually straightforward
to show that okay if you have continuous MDP's
right then it becomes a little trickier, so
we will discuss this when I am actually starting
the proofs in the next class, why is it that
there exists a optimal policy at all right,
so we will discuss this in the next class
when I'm talking about proves right.
So right now, we will try to do the equivalent
of Bellman equations for V star right, I mean
likewise i can define an optimal value function
for q, what would be the optimal value function
for q, yeah another solution is there something
that sound right, what is problem here so
we need to put that pi thing here right, so
what I what I want you to appreciate here
is that even though I am talking about optimal
policies, I still the first action it take
easy
right the first actually take is a, always
here whether I am talking about optimal so,
it is only after i take a I behave optimally
so that is why this max is after, in fact
I can remove the max here and I can insert
it anything that comes before it is it not
influenced by the max right.
Because I take a fixed action it is something
which you have to keep in mind so whenever
you talk about Q star S,A right, the A is
still fixed it might not be the best A to
do right in fact, I can have a Q star a defined
for this action here, wait I can have a Q
star here defined for this action also for
each one of these actions I can have a Q star
defined right, this is it so the Q star of
the down action will essentially be minus
1 plus V star of going from here to the goal,
right in the Q star of this action will be
minus 1 plus V star going here assuming is
deterministic, otherwise it will be minus
1 plus point nine times the value of going
from here and point nine times the value of
going from if it is stochastic right.
so I can think of defining Q star for even
sub optimal action this is one thing if I
want to keep in mind so it's not like Q star
is defined only for optimal actions let there,
okay great, so now we have these things so
let us try to see what we can do so, I want
to do V star (s) say I want to find V star
of s, so what would V star of s equal to?
Do you think in terms of Q star ? So what
do you think V star of s will be in terms
of Q star , so what is Q star tell me?
If I take action A and behave optimally thereafter
right so, what can V star be, I mean that
is essentially behaving optimally from the
current state.
Let's say I am going to look at okay which
one whatever gives me the best reward on taking
a and then behaving optimally thereafter right
so think about what this expression is?
This expression is essentially okay.
I behave according to a and after that I behave
optimally right, so that is essentially this
expression right and I am taking a max here
which essentially means said okay, which is
the action that gives me this?
The best of this expression and that I cannot
behave more optimally than that, because it
is only the first action I have a choice here
after that I'm assuming and behaving optimally
whatever is optimal behavior right.
So i am not talking about the recovering the
optimal behavior yet right, I'm only talking
about finding what the optimal value function
is right, I am assuming after-action a and
behaving optimally, so now the only thing
i need to figure out is what is action a and
I need to pick that action a says that when
you add the reward for taking mediate or what
for taking action a and the return for behaving
optimally they are after I get the most.
So this is essentially very intuitive way
of defining what the optimal value function
is now I can expand this you can say it's
max over a summation s prime and that is what
max over pi is say max over pi V pi V star
sort of the V star is prime.
e
This is how we got that so, this is called
the bellman optimality equation for V star
likewise you can write a bell but optimality
equation for, you start have to be why not
wait whether it is some policy there is no
question of some policy will give you a higher
policy even why I gave you all the optimal
policies tell me which one will do that?
Just think about it if that is some policy
that will do that then I will basically change
the action to that I mean that has to be optimum
right if there is going right this does not
have the same values going up going up as
a higher value than going right, then going
up has to be optimal going right cannot be
optimal because then if I do the max only
one will apply the other one won't appear
right.
so one other thing so I have been talking
only about deterministic optimal policies
right I said there are like there are 12 elements
and there are two options there did not be
so, as long as I have a policy which are saying
only non zero probabilities to the optimal
actions right that is also an optimal policy
so, in this state I can choose with probability
point 5 to go up or probability point 5 to
go right, right so, point 5 do up, point 5
go right that is also an optimal policy right
it could be any combination as long as I have
zero probability for going right or going
down right then I am self happy then it is
an optimal policy right so, there is an infinite
number of optimal policies is an infinite
number of optimal policy.
so nowhere is the next question I want to
ask so given a value function how will you
recover optimal policy from that because,
I give you V star how you recover an optimal
policy from that so I have to know figure
out what action I have to take in each state
right and I have to take that action that
achieves the max right so, what I mean by
achieves the max so in the case of V star
actually take an action figure out where I
will end up right, and take that action that
gives me the max over that right so, what
I mean by where I land up at so I pick some
action right then i sum over s prime sorry,
so this is the utility for taking an action
right.
so I have to pick an action that gives me
so given a V star this is how I will recover
a PI star right yeah depends on how you how
you implement the arc max that if the ark
max you can write it such a way that you will
return any of the maximizes then you will
get a deterministic policy or you can return
your arm access that it returns all the maximizes
then you can think of having some kind of
uniform probability distribution over the
Maximize it can be uniform or it could be
one way or but if, you think of arc max is
returning some arbitrarily returning one of
the maximizes will get a deterministic policy
right this is one way of recovering optimal
policies from the optimal value function okay.
so the little trickier I still need to know
p and c need to know the expected values and
other things even if somebody gives me the
value function I still need to know the rest
of the parameters of the MDP for me to recover
the optimal policy.
But suppose somebody gives me the Q function
how I will recommend the optimal policy, we
think about looking at the expression there
right in the arc max is exactly this right.
so
if i give you the q functions if I give me
Q star I do not need all this.
what I am doing is essentially looking at
one step right if I do a okay what will happen?
Right.
so I am looking at the outcome and then trying
to make the decision the best decision based
on that outcome right but here the Q star
I do not even have to do that one step look
at it right I can just be greedy with respect
to my current Q star and I will pi star makes
sense so, if i give you V star and Q star
now we can know how to find pi star and we
also we spoke about how we can solve the bellman
equation for V pi and Q pi, can you solve
the bellman equation like that for V star
and Q star , I have a system of n equations
in n variables, the same thing as before.
Can I solve it?
What's the problem?
it's not linear right so it says i have this
max here it makes it the nonlinear system
of equations so you'll have to figure out
how we are going to solve it right.
So this is what we will look at in the next
class the next layer what I will do is first
show that well in multiple ways so that V
pi is unique and then show that V star is
unique right, and then come up with a talk
about multiple ways of solving for we started
well not only this will b V pi can we'll talk
about multiple ways of solving for V star
, in fact the rest of the course in some senses
figuring out multiple ways of solving for
V star and Q star under different assumptions
okay, how much information you have, how much
data you have and so on so forth right, so
great so any questions?
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved